<DOC>
<DOCNO>
EN-9807042A20DM317
</DOCNO>
<LANG>
EN
</LANG>
<TEXT>
<STNO>0001</STNO>
Firm accused of touting tainted blood abroad
<STNO>0002</STNO>
    Three former presidents of the Osaka company, Green Cross Co., are standing trial for their alleged role in the infection of HIV -- the virus that causes acquired immune deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) -- of possibly thousands of hemophiliacs in Japan by marketing unheated blood-clotting products. 
<STNO>0003</STNO>
    The company's unsuccessful attempts to market the dangerous products in East European countries are detailed in in-house documents, copies of which were obtained by the Mainichi. 
<STNO>0004</STNO>
    One of the documents, dated May 7, 1986, and titled "Effective utilization of inventory -- consideration of export," stated that the company had begun negotiations with foreign pharmaceutical companies to export the unheated products. 
<STNO>0005</STNO>
    The talks were carried out through an American subsidiary of Green Cross, said the document, which carried the seal of an executive of the Osaka company's sales planning department. 
<STNO>0006</STNO>
    The results of the negotiations -- all negative -- were reported in another document dated July 31, 1986, with the potential buyers saying they didn't want the products because they carried too high a risk of being contaminated with HIV.     The apparent motive for Green Cross to attempt to go overseas was to make up for a sharp decline in domestic sales of the products following the introduction of safer, heat-treated versions four months earlier. 
<STNO>0007</STNO>
    In January 1986, when heat-treated products were introduced, Green Cross shipped 615 units of unheated versions of the products. 
<STNO>0008</STNO>
The figure plunged to 58 units the following month and then to 15 in May. 
<STNO>0009</STNO>
    The company was able to continue marketing the unheated products because the Health and Welfare Ministry never banned their sale even after their risk of HIV contamination became well known. 
<STNO>0010</STNO>
    The documents in question have been seized by the Osaka District Public Prosecutors Office, which indicted the three former Green Cross heads in the tainted blood scandal. 
<STNO>0011</STNO>
Prosecutors plan to use the documents as evidence that the company favored profits over safety. 
<STNO>0012</STNO>
    The defendants have admitted to the allegation of professional negligence resulting in death. 
<STNO>0013</STNO>
Of the three former executives, Renzo Matsushita was at the helm of Green Cross when it attempted to sell the unheated products overseas. 
<STNO>0014</STNO>
    Prior to his arrival at Green Cross, Matsushita headed the Health Ministry's Pharmaceutical Affairs Bureau, the section in charge of screening drugs for use in Japan. 
<STNO>0015</STNO>
    In separate damage lawsuits involving hemophiliacs who became infected with HIV through tainted blood-clotting products, the Health Ministry and five pharmaceutical companies have agreed to compensate the victims in 1996. 
<STNO>0016</STNO>
    Of the nation's estimated 5,000 hemophiliacs, about 40 percent are said to have become infected with the AIDS virus through tainted blood products mainly in the early 1980s. 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
